Local History Collection
Ivoryton Library Association
Local History Collection
1860-present
1880-1910, 1940-44, 1982
Ivoryton Library Association
2000-001
29 37 boxes, 5 binders, 4 file drawers
An artificial collection that documents the history of the village of Ivoryton, a village within the town of Essex, CT. Ivoryton was a factory town built around Comstock, Cheney & Co., an ivory processing plant and the primary employer until the 1980's.
Restrictions
Collection open and available for research use. Copyright restrictions apply
Acquisition Information
This is and artificial collection consisting of documents, photos and other items acquired by the Ivoryton Library Association through donations. Future additions to this collection are expected.
Biography
Ivoryton is one of three villages in the town of Essex, CT. The village was built up around the Comstock, Cheney & Co. ivory processing plant as an example of industrial paternalism. Before the factory closed its doors in 1989, it was the main employer for village residents. The factory built or helped build a store, a school, the Ivoryton Library, the Ivoryton Playhouse and over 100 houses, as well as factory buildings that are now in use by other businesses.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection documents the history of the village of Ivoryton primarily, although some references to Centerbrook and Essex Village, the other two villages in the town of Essex, are included. These materials were acquired by the library through donations over the past several decades. Many are of unknown origin. Included are pamphlets, manuscripts, magazines and magazine articles, research papers, audiovisual materials, newsletters, legal documents, census reports, cookbooks, maps, scrapbooks, newspapers and newspaper clippings, postcards, photographs, documents and realia. While there are frequent mentions of Comstock, Cheney & Co. and Pratt, Read & Co., the two names for the ivory factory in town, ,the materials mainly show the history of the other business and organization. There are also personal reminiscences as well as a large amount of material on the Falls River Flood of 1982.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into 3 series: Series I: Documents and Ephemera, Series II: Photographs and Postcards, Series III: Newspaper Clippings. As there was no original order and very little provenance, the items in this collection are artificially arranged first geographically, then by subject.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Ivoryton (Conn.); Comstock, Cheney & Co.; Pratt, Read & Co.; Essex (Conn.); Floods--1980-2000.; Schools--Connecticut.; Falls River (Conn.)
Separated Material
Oversized scrapbooks, newspapers, maps and books are located in the oversized Local History area in the main circulation room of the Ivoryton Library
- Inventory
  - Documents - Centerbook and Essex (town), 1892-2013 (Box 1)
  - Documents - Essex (Village), 1920-1998 (Box 2)
  - Documents - Ivoryton, 1880-2009 (Box 3A)
  - Documents - Ivoryton, cont., 1909-1982 (Box 3B)
  - Miscellaneous legal-size documents, 1860-1980 (Box 4)
  - Research papers, various authors and subjects, 1940-2006 (Box 5)
  - Essex Cub Scouts scrapbooks, 1963-1981 (Box 6)
  - fundraising cookbooks, various sources, 1898-1996 (Box 7)
  - WWII - Frank McGill badge & certificate, 1859 (Box 8)
  - Audiovisual items - audio cassettes, CDs, DVDs, 1876 (Box 9)
  - Artifacts found at 22 Chestnut St, Ivoryton, Lindburgh family, undated (Box 10)
  - Oversize - County Atlas of Middlesex County by F.W. Beers, 1875 (Box 11)
  - Oversize - Flood, 1936,sScrapbooks (Box 12)
  - Oversize - Flood, 1982, newspaper supplements (Box 13)
  - Oversize - Flood, 1982, scrapbooks (Box 14)
  - Oversize - Miscellaneous oversize items, 1937-1987 (Box 15)
  - Oversize - Micellaneous oversize items, cont, 1942-1967 (Box 16)
  - Scrapbook, Jay Johnson, Building the Baldwin Bridge, 1948 (Box 17)
  - Africa, ivory trade, Zanzibar, 1890-1910 (Box Photo 1)
  - Centerbrook, Essex Village, 1898-1998 (Box Photo 2)
  - Ivoryton: businesses, 1900-2011 (Box Photo 3A)
  - Ivoryton: churches, houses, 1888-2003 (Box Photo 3B)
  - Ivoryton: landscapes, people, 1910-2003 (Box Photo 4)
  - Ivoryton: Playhouse, schools, transportation, 1911-1979 (Box Photo 5)
  - Ivoryton Grammar School: class photos, 1900-1930s (Box Photo 6)
  - Ivoryton Grammar School: class photos, 1946-1950s (Box Photo 7)
  - Falls River Flood, 1982 (Box Photo 8)
  - Ivoryton Library, 1888-2017 (Box Photo 9)
  - Postcards, 1905-2003 (Box Photo 10)
  - Comstock, Cheney & Co, 1896-1936 (Box Photo 11)
  - C.C & Co., baseball, bleach houses, ivory, 1890-1951 (Box Photo12)
  - Pratt, Read & Co. (also P.R & Co, Deep River), 1890-1988 (Box Photo13)
  - Pratt, Read & Co., 1959 demonlition, 1982 flood, 1959-1982 (Box Photo 14)
  - Pratt, Read & Co., 1982 flood (Box Photo 15)
  - Village of Ivoryton, 1949-2015 (Box NC 1)
  - Ivoryton Library, 1939-2017 (Box NC 2)
  - Town of Essex, 1928-2005 (Box NC 3)
  - Ivoryton Playhouse, people, 1978-2013 (Box NC 4)